A Guide to the Papers of Anne Spencer and the Spencer Family, 1829, 1864-2007
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Manuscripts and Poems (Box-folder 17:7-22:55)
  - Dated Notebooks (Box-folder 20:3-20:12)
    - [1936], n.d. Notebook, containing the following (in order of their appearance): Notes about library classes or meetings, appearing throughout this volume, including Jackson Davis and General Education Board, and Mr. Smith of the Rosenwald Fund,; quote [from Spencer?] "Let us be like trees that yield their fruit to those who throw stones at them"; discussion of definition as "man's weakest trap for catching God, to catch and confine" with examples explicit as to type of person, such as "the publican says goodly fear"; a veiled reference to cruelties of Nazism; the lack of a soul in hypocrites who steal the soil of the black man, take the black man himself from his kraal-house door, his salt, water, or other goods and then whisper Christ to him, like a bird looks at a snake "and neither the twain go home again" (scattered over several pages); Staff Organization with notes about library work, Miss Rose, Miss Smith, and Miss Hall; note about Chinese sailors; description of a funeral of an old man; statement beginning, "I know my soul to be sinful, I believe it to be honest"; a version of the poem, "Letter to My Sister" titled here "Warning to Women"; "Emotions"; description of "Insurance Superintendent"; "Warren's [Spectacles?]"; "Elmer Gantry" and questioning settled religious sentiment; new race law "pushed as many of us in as out, alas"; Lucile's Frederick; back-biting; "Opening Chapter - Jerry, I want to be, what I've never been, I want to be happy."; "Old Lady Warren"; a story about Zilla, who "felt no excitement over the coming of Clay's latest lion"; quotation about books; statement about human behavior; musings following the statement, "If you want a pretty comfortable state of being, you got to have a lot of fools to maintain it."; statement, "I cannot blame them. To gladly be a Negro in a day like this takes more moral courage and sense than God suffered most white men to have."; note about a story, "Old Lady Warren's house burns - she moves in with P. Clay temporarily and Zilla vows to make it as short as temporary could be made"; list of books; "Interlude: Warren's Wife" pages; and a note about a Richmond colored waiting room (Box-folder 20:5))
    - 1941, n.d. Notebook, consisting of writings within a bank register book, on the inside front cover, she writes that both "supply men" and "front line men" have one purpose, which is to "make the world safe for Tory-land." She sees no difference between [Charles?] Lindbergh and Georgia's [Eugene?] Talmadge. On the back cover, is a draft of a letter to Mr. Inger about Civil Rights; and a cryptic story of an unnamed, former poor-white woman who sought to find a better ancestry to support her newly accumulated possessions, such as membership in the D.A.R. and other such alphabetical extensions. (Box-folder 20:6))
    - [ca. 1965-1968?], n.d. Notebook, apparently containing notes and responses of Anne Spencer to a series of interviews of Eric Hoffer by Eric Sevareid (CBS) on television; discusses and disagrees with Langston [Hughes'] comment about "dishwater gives back no images"; the televised debates between William F. Buckley, Jr. and Gore Vidal [during the 1968 Democratic Party convention?]; observations about truth; John Gunther; education and drop-outs; the down-trodden of the world from Saudi Arabia to the U.S.; discusses Poe quotation "Take your beak from out my heart" in relation to Allen Tate; "For good reading" a paragraph about the English language; comment about "helpful adverse criticism"; quotation "Whatever we crave we cannot have to possess is total loss. To hold is but to desire more again."; Prodigal sons, "Whatever we sell our lives for is a final bargain: it cannot be exchanged."; list of books; comment about Sir Walter Scott; and in the very back of the notebook, "Empathy" praising her husband's sister and Wiley Thompson; and mention of Edwin Embree (1883-1950), president of the Julius Rosenwald Fundation. (Box-folder 20:7))
    - 1967-1972 Notebook, containing the following (in order of their appearance): a note about the Creator, who left remorse to man; draft of a letter to her "dear Kin"; a note referring to "B.C." about the English language; "Sir Walter Scott versus Ben Johnson"; note about [Abraham Lincoln?]; "a stark high place of ash and cinder"; her preference for a gentle man until a hell raiser is required; mention of the Carson show, Bill Buckley, and Bob Newhart, all in the context of laughter versus humor; Henry Steele Commager and his book, A Continuing Journey, Spencer writes "My voyage I'm being on now is death much delayed"; "There is no place but this where four such roads meet"; "Bastion at Newark" (see other manuscripts with same title in Box 17); comments about Dorothy Thompson (1894-1961), columnist; draft of a letter to Lee Greene about going to [Randolph Macon Women's College?] to hear Ralph [Abernathy?], which also mentions John Brown and Harriet Tubman, and Agnes Repplier; notes about first chapter of Genesis; "Influence" with two lines, "When the valley lily doth shake its cup// deeper must go the fisherman's net at sea"; "Dark Man O'Mine" poem very similar to "Black Man O' Mine"; and a poem beginning, "There's a rose new planted I've never seen." (Box-folder 20:8))
    - [post 1969?] Notebook, containing the following thoughts and topics: a charwoman going to heaven and being allowed to clean and clean; on books; a thing of beauty and James Stephens; God; religion and the visit to the moon; draft of a letter to Mr. Ferrone; a piece about astronauts, titled "Sure, this is overkill"; in the back of the notebook, nationalism and peace; words too timid to use; and newborns and infants (Box-folder 20:9))
    - [ca. 1971-1974] Notebook containing personal reminiscences and stories, beginning with a draft of a letter from Spencer to Lee Greene about his frustrations in trying "to move my life into the sun"; continuing with her marriage, mention of the wife of Thomas [W.?] Fleming (1874-1948), black Republican councilman from Cleveland, Lethia Cousins Fleming (1876-1963), Annie's delayed honeymoon trip to Washington, D.C. and Baltimore when her oldest child was twelve, and two unrelated manuscript fragments. Greene did a typed transcript of most of this notebook and it has also been placed in this folder. (Box-folder 20:10))
    - 1972 Jun 24 Notebook kept by Lee Greene containing notes about Anne Spencer's work and life used in his book, Time's Unfading Garden, including notes from an interview called "Visit to Anne Spencer, June 24, 1972," 15 pages. Specific poems mentioned include: "The Skeptic" and "White Things" (page 8-9); poem about Terence MacSwiney, also called "Terence, Terence" (page 9); "Generals" and a poem about John Brown (page 9 and 15); her spider poem "Po Little Lib" (page 12); "The Wife Woman" (page 15) and a story about a crow named Joe (page 11). (Box-folder 20:11))
    - 1974 Jul 2-3, n.d. Notebook kept by Lee Greene containing notes about Anne Spencer's work and life used in his book, Time's Unfading Garden, most taken during a visit to Anne Spencer, July 2-3, 1974, including notes on American culture; two lists of books, possibly for classes; list of things to questions to ask Spencer about including: "Any Wife," friendship with Georgia Johnson, William Stafford, and Murrell Edmunds about "Ghetto Night"; notes about the Terence MacSwiney poem, "Earth Songs," and "Wife Woman"; copy of poem "1975" and notes about "Po Little Lib"; and John Brown and "The Lemming." (Box-folder 20:12))
  - Undated Notebooks (Box-folder 21:1-21:19)
    - n.d. Notebook A, with literary and other allusions, including Bernard Schwartz, The Nigger of the Narcissus, William Faulkner, D.H. Lawrence, Alfred North Whitehead, "whodunits" by Dorothy Sayers and Agatha Christie, Jude the Obscure, and Edgar A. Poe and "The Raven" (Box-folder 21:1))
    - n.d. Notebook B, concerning thoughts about poetry, language, and words, with mention of John Brown's hanging and Harriet Tubman (Box-folder 21:2))
    - n.d. Notebook C, containing the poem "Epitome," with notes on "I Have a Friend" and "At the Carnival" all with a typed transcription by [Lee Greene?], plus material on "Miss Lucy" and the family (Box-folder 21:3))
    - n.d. Notebook D, containing several titled manuscript pieces, "The Kings of Time," and "USA - Man," which mentions a Reverend Wilkie and Bob Moses of Knoxville, Tennessee; a notation to include in the John Brown poem, "G- Heaven is ever anxious to contain its own mistakes" and possibly another page to include at the back of the notebook; and "Nature has protected its future finely." (Box-folder 21:4))
    - n.d. Notebook E, containing comments about the use of guns against [student?] protests; if God was dead in Newark; Stefan Lorant, who did a picture biography of Abraham Lincoln; inertia; humanhood (several pages); 25 word list, possibly of flower names; comparison of the United States to a long term marriage where each partner has "to exchange and endure more and longer passels of habits each could do without"; countries "pogromming the Jews since AD instead of thanking them for a God rising upon the water - and were inorganic and organic effulgence of a complete existence"; her senses "now all my -5 are slightly impaired save my sense of gratitude and affection"; and a comment about John Milton (Box-folder 21:5))
    - n.d. Notebook F, comments on clothing and hats; draft of a fan letter to children's writer, Effie Lee [Newsome] (1885-1979), discussing her library work and poetry, lists by educators of what children need to learn and when, using as an example the partition of Poland and the book Pan Michael, resulting in "no adventures, no surprises. No standing stark and bare on Patmos as some cataclysmic revelation of Power of Beauty rolls over us. A lot of us know that by 'abundant life' Christ meant that the soul ought to be held together by a few purple patches"; and comments about a picture in the [Christian Science Monitor?] of seven poor-white men. (Box-folder 21:6))
    - n.d. Notebook G, (largely illegible) discussing the human mind and selfhood; possible poem beginning "occurs the salient storm" and another "I met a little Harlem girl, she was 16 years"; forgetting one of her mother's axioms; a statement about poetry, "There is nothing that many people dislike more than poetry: The grubstake mind seems not to know or care that is poetry." (Box-folder 21:7))
    - n.d. Notebook H, begins with "Far As I Know" which discusses W.E.B. Du Bois and his sense of humor; a start of a poem dedicated to Pop; a poem "Dust Bowl"; ending line from "Po Little Lib"; oblique reference to the fable of Ralph Waldo Emerson about the mountain and the squirrel; "Note for Norton" publishers, about her diatribe; poem "Big Ditch"; draft of a letter to Geoffrey Matthew about the progress of his Learning Tree and quoting a few lines from her poem "O Pinions or words on a wing"; "Genealogy" which tells stories from her earliest memories of childhood and details about her parents, Joel and Sarah Louise; "Index to Tape Pronouns," which includes comments about history, "The best things in history books never happened," survival, a laundress on her street, and memories of her earliest schooling; discussion of semantics; more memories of the conflict between her father and mother; note on the verso about Mencken and her work; recollections of her early life and marriage to Edward Spencer (6 pages); "Dubois" perhaps a quote?; several pages that appear to match the ideas in "Bastion at Newark"; and near the very end of the notebook, discussion of what makes a "bourgeoisie boor" and a statement "I'm glad I was born in the beginning of a world the Creator now regrets He even made - instead of its end." Also present was a loose page, containing a poem about an "awesome ring, feeding on arc after arc." (Box-folder 21:8))
    - n.d. Notebook I, quote on cover from [Ronald?] Reagan, with a comment by Anne Spencer, "So there we have a man of minimum intelligence with a plusful mouth"; comments about archaeology, braggadocio, and what is wrong with our seminaries; Stokely [Carmichael?] and McKissnic; quote "Sometimes, I think if life does not knock you down when you are nine you won't have any sense when you are ninety"; "Lincoln is Still at Newark"; note about Nicolay and chattledom; "weather for today huge bronze inertness; observation that once "the word is got" by humans we begin a marvelous process called "o-pinion or the flying mind-on-wing" and "There's Mr. Eric Hoffer lonely reader of word books, encyclopedia, and the sea at waterfront"; wishes for her reader to hope along with Flannery O'Connor that "Everything That Rises Must Converge"; "On Your Noe and youth; God refusing to answer the prayers of the righteous because there are too many; comment about Corra Harris and her Recording Angel; statement that she wanted books and lucre, needed in that order; mention of Stefan Lorant; "Newark Junction" about bronze statue of Lincoln (see previous entry for this notebook "Lincoln is Still at Newark"; brief mention of "a minute Selma long"; reference to "Stanchion Root"; reference to Eric Hoffer; quote from Spencer "The turbulent American mixture has the painful honor of plowing up this unfallowed earth. It just took this rough unhallowed mix to do it"; "energized greedy" saw that [African Americans?] "could be ductile educated, insured, medicated, baptized, funeralized - apart to their social benefit"; "An Old Man Remembers Stanchion": "Another April"; "Luck" is from childhood to have known those esp. willing enough to open a special book in deep space to your kind of mind even just to let you know there is a book"; beginnings of a poem about taking two to break through walls; "For G[od's?] Dustmen"; and "Golden Dustman?" (Box-folder 21:9))
    - n.d. Notebook J, "Note for JB [John Brown]" (4 pages); poem "Tragedy Great" also entitled "Po Little Lib"; poem "Derived from Any Wife to Any Husband"; additional material for her John Brown poem; additional John Brown page in middle of notebook; manuscript of several pages beginning "the lately escaped harem of Sheba and Nefertiti" (Box-folder 21:10))
    - n.d. Notebook K, comments on de Tocqueville, Spiro Agnew, Uncle Remus, and Mary Todd Lincoln, all in the very front of the notebook (Box-folder 21:11))
    - n.d. Notebook L, manuscript "All's Clear"; poem "Derivative Title: Any Wife to Any Husband" both at the beginning of the notebook (Box-folder 21:12))
    - n.d. Notebook M, fragment of poem "The Lemming"; story about her daughter applying for money to study psychology, three persons passed tests at Columbia, a Jewish girl from New York City, one Negro girl from Lynchburg, and a Negro youth from Christiansburg, Virginia; comparison of H.L. Mencken and E.B. White attitude to a purple phrase; poem "Haiku (One)"; draft of a letter to Mrs. Paradis; and draft of a letter to an unnamed couple (Box-folder 21:13))
    - n.d. Notebook N, begins with comments about Richard Nixon; manuscript about ladies as loaf-givers according to Ruskin, and all females as ladies in the South, an observation about her mother being an "Uncle Remus"; and a manuscript beginning "the coldest thing this side of the Antarctic is money" (Box-folder 21:14))
    - n.d. Notebook O, begins with reference to a quote from Saint Paul in I Corinthians about giving our bodies to be burned; a manuscript observation "She was an alert person at the mere suggestion that your skin - the skin of your spirit, was about to be shed, she reached for the salt"; observation about herself "Personal irateness has kept me alive this side of death these fifteen years beyond my death date"; note about Mr. Lincoln and Mr. Jones; "Capote: First Book"; a manuscript about poetry "Poetry for Highs [Highbrows?]" mentioning Marvell, Donne, E.E. [Cummings], and Browning, Edna St. Vincent Millay and her sonnet ["Epitaph for the Race of Man"] speaking of the dinosaur's womb, Millay's "Conversation at Midnight," and Robert Nathan; poem "Incidence" also called "Po Little Lib"; slaves and Indians made possible physical survival; the shepherd of our little flock; manuscript for "Stanchion Root" (five pages); mention of Romain Gary (1914-1980) and the relationship between humor and laughter (Box-folder 21:15))
    - n.d. Notebook P, begins with statement "Your Christ-part demands our humility and demands that it be humble as a pride of lions" and "piety is not for earth…" followed by a description of the various races of earth; threat of the proles (George Orwellian term); "Poetry by heart"; reading and the threat of banning, such as the work Amahl and the Night Visitors by Gian Carlo Menotti (1911-2007) in a Mississippi school because one of the kings was black; furnished the antidote to Proleism; "On Spelling or Thinking" originally intended as "The Going of the Proles," speaking of Mr. Allen Tate, one of the "high tor southern agrarians (who know so little, no doubt, of agronomy)" and his remark to teach above their pupil's heads; the praise of Louis Untermeyer for Spencer in his book American Poets Since 1900; Told of a book report by a 7 th grader on That Was A Time about the beautiful relationship between the Big House and the Slave Quarters, ending with "That, she said was a hell of a time!"; the use of the word "sob"; and a loose sheet manuscript beginning "not poems by me who happened to be a Negro we are what we are by a relentless encircling design. And with all my warring bloods whatever it is that's called Negro has conquered and as I told you over forty years when the few things I had published cuckoo in other author's nest that is the way I like it" (Box-folder 21:16))
    - n.d. Notebook Q, begins with observations about "nonrepressed words"; "William Allen White (1868-1944) is dead" heard on her radio; mention of Joseph Fort Newton; settlement of Australia and Georgia; draft of a letter of condolence to Frankie about Louis, "friendship is such a tenuous thing it must be strong and deathless to exist at all"; one of the iterations of her spider poems; and another manuscript about a bronze statue of Lincoln (Box-folder 21:17))
    - n.d. Notes by Anne Spencer, including: The Adventures of Huck Finn; English history; People; Russian history; The True Believer by Eric Hoffer; Miguel de Una Muno y Jugo, a Spanish philosopher and writer; and Yang and Yin (Box-folder 21:18))
    - ca. 1972-1973, n.d. Notes by Lee Greene concerning Anne Spencer and her Work (Box-folder 21:19))
  - Poems and Other (Box-folder 21:20-22:55)
    - n.d. Poem beginning "All is Told About It" (Creation) (Box-folder 21:20))
    - n.d. Poem beginning "Autumn is [a] blatant fellow chin resting on a cloud" (Box-folder 21:21))
    - n.d. Poem beginning "I'd shame for a season, date, or star" (Box-folder 21:22))
    - n.d. Poem beginning "Palette-heart the artist drew" (Box-folder 21:23))
    - n.d. Poem beginning "Spirit and bone" (Box-folder 21:24))
    - n.d. Poem beginning "stove surrounded by virgin trees" (Box-folder 21:25))
    - n.d. Poem fragment concerning Ruth Brown (see Greene page 171) (Box-folder 21:26))
    - n.d. Poem "Amends" (Box-folder 22:1))
    - n.d. Poem "Any Wife to Any Husband A Derived Poem," two handwritten versions, one called "Portents" and another "Life and Love"; on one of these handwritten versions is another handwritten poem called "Villagers" later published with the title "Neighbors"; also present is a small notebook about the derivation of the poem (Box-folder 22:2))
    - ca. 1924, [post 1969] Poem "Ascetic" TMs and various drafts, part of "Lord Songs," with one draft is a prose manuscript entitled "Erranticies" on the verso; one typed version also includes the short poems "Failure" and "Liability" (Greene 119-120) (Box-folder 22:3))
    - n.d. Poem "At the Carnival" (Box-folder 22:4))
    - n.d. Poem "Before the Feast of Shushan" (Box-folder 22:5))
    - n.d. Poem "Big Ditch and the River" (Box-folder 22:6))
    - n.d. Poem "Black Man O' Mine" (Box-folder 22:7))
    - n.d. Poem "But Why? Suggested by Richard Harris" (Box-folder 22:8))
    - n.d. Poem "Cowardice" (Box-folder 22:9))
    - n.d. Poem "Creed" (Box-folder 22:10))
    - [post 1961]-74, n.d. Poem "A Dream of John Brown" with notes (Box-folder 22:11))
    - n.d. Poem "A Dream of John Brown" notebook (Box-folder 22:12))
    - n.d. Poem "Dunbar" (Box-folder 22:13))
    - n.d. Poem "Epitome," with notes on "I Have a Friend" and "At the Carnival" (Box-folder 22:14))
    - n.d. Poem "An Evening of 'Readings' in a Strange City" (Box-folder 22:15))
    - n.d. Poem "Failure," part of the "Lord Songs" or "Earth Songs" (Box-folder 22:16))
    - n.d. Poem "For E.A.S." On the verso is a manuscript beginning "A set of Dunbar aperients. Try these on your pupils" (Box-folder 22:17))
    - [1947], n.d. Poem "For Jim, Easter Eve" or "To James Weldon Johnson Easter Eve (1938-1948)" (Box-folder 22:18))
    - n.d. Poem "For a Passing Hearse" (Box-folder 22:19))
    - n.d. Poem "Grapes: Still-Life" (Box-folder 22:20))
    - n.d. Poem "Hart Crest" in a small notebook, with another manuscript mentioning the Kaiser's throne (Box-folder 22:21))
    - n.d. Poem "He Said:" (Box-folder 22:22))
    - 1972 Aug 18, n.d. Poem "I Have a Friend" (Box-folder 22:23))
    - [1930s], 1972 Aug 18 Poem "Innocence" (Box-folder 22:24))
    - [post 1939] Poem "Instans Tyrannus" (Box-folder 22:25))
    - n.d. Poem "Invocation for a Christmas Baby" (Box-folder 22:26))
    - n.d. Poem "Lady, Lady" (Box-folder 22:27))
    - n.d. Poem "The Lemming: O Sweden," one draft of the poem has other manuscript on the back about God and the "new novel" writing (Box-folder 22:28))
    - 1972 Aug 18, n.d. Poem "Letter to My Sister" (Box-folder 22:29))
    - n.d. Poem "Liability" (Box-folder 22:30))
    - n.d. Poem "Life-Long, Poor Browning" (Box-folder 22:31))
    - n.d. Poem "Lines to a Nasturtium" including a version of the poem entitled "A Lover Muses" originally written on the kitchen door, but now also on paper in another hand (Box-folder 22:32))
    - n.d. Poem "Luther P. Jackson" (Box-folder 22:33))
    - n.d. Poem "Neighbors" (Box-folder 22:34))
    - 1974, n.d. Poem "1975" including typescript versions, a published version from the Central Virginia Community College Office of Continuing Education Elderly Resource Booklet with its accompanying explanatory letter from Lafayette Robinson, November 22, 1974 (Box-folder 22:35))
    - n.d. Poem "O Pinions or words on wing," one typed version also has other typescript manuscripts included (Box-folder 22:36))
    - [post 1964 Jan], n.d. Poem "Po' Little Lib"; also entitled "[A Garden] Incident," "Half-inch brown spider," and "Tragedy" also with a note about the title (see the discussion in Greene, pages 147-148) (Box-folder 22:37))
    - n.d. Poem "Prayer" (Box-folder 22:38))
    - n.d. Poem "Questing" (Box-folder 22:39))
    - [1974 Fall] Poem "Reliques," unfinished, according to Greene, the poem was about her husband Edward and was planned as companion piece to "Po' Little Lib" (Box-folder 22:40))
    - n.d. Poem "Requiem" (Box-folder 22:41))
    - n.d. Poem "Rime for the Christmas Baby (At 48 Webster Place, Orange)" (Box-folder 22:42))
    - n.d. Poem "The Rock" (Box-folder 22:43))
    - n.d. Poem "The Sévignés" (Box-folder 22:44))
    - n.d. Poem "Stanchion Roots" notebook containing drafts of the narrative (Box-folder 22:45))
    - 1974 Jan 18, n.d. Poem "Substitution" (Box-folder 22:46))
    - [1972], n.d. Poem "Terence, Terence" (Box-folder 22:47))
    - n.d. Poem "Translation" (Box-folder 22:48))
    - n.d. Poem "We Are Such Friends" (Box-folder 22:49))